VINU RAMASAMY

(224) 433-1115 Chicago, IL 60169

vinur01@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/vinuramasamy/

SENIOR MANAGEMENT – PRODUCT DEVELOPMENT

Excels at Product R&D, Strategies, & Solutions

20+ years of leading product development experience. High-energy and high-performing leader with extensive success in application product R&D and vision. Leading and building winning global team dynamics and driving culture change. Driving customer / business realization functionalities with focus on simplicity. Strong capabilities in forming and implementing creative product strategies and solutions. Drive new technology adoption. Proactive in addressing systemic issues. Challenge the status quo. Oversee operational efficiency to maximize business results with start-up mentality. Effective communications skills, succinct to all levels of the organization.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

Cross-Functional Global Team Leadership | Product Vision & Development | R&D
Organizational Design & Development | Strategic Planning & Leadership | Product Roadmap |
Operational Process, Productivity & Efficiency Improvement | Customer Collaboration

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Motorola Solutions Inc., **Software Enterprise**, Schaumburg & Chicago, IL **Director of Software Engineering**

2015 - Present

Lead the product vision, strategy & development of mobile apps and middleware data services platform that enables the next generation work group communications (new business initiative) apps ecosystem.

Strategic Technology Leadership

- Led the creation of Intelligent Middleware data services platform / infrastructure with identity management, common address book, group management, location, presence and messaging key services for public safety and work group communications application ecosystem. - Enabled winning a big customer contract (UKHO) with demonstration of new services and capabilities as proof of concepts.
- Evolution of Intelligent Middleware data services platform that is secure, scalable and cloud agnostic, i.e. can be deployed on private data centers and public cloud (AWS), leveraging microservices based architecture, open source software (e.g. XMPP for messaging solution, CoreOS, Kafka,...) and 3rd-party software to enable ability to add new services with high velocity along with CI/CD framework.
- Conceptualized strategy and built the apps (Android/iOS/Windows) team in Chicago from ground up to create an ecosystem across multiple verticals with primary focus on public safety with apps SDK enabling 3rd-party developer program aligning with corporate apps ecosystem growth strategy.
- Drove and deployed Sandbox environment in AWS for 3rd-party developer program, customer demos & trials
 resulted in sales opportunities; revenue doubled on location data services for existing radio systems.
- Actively involved in business strategy / offering option generation and new customer RFPs.

Cross-Functional Global Organization Leadership

- Expanded the development team to ~165+ globally (Krakow, Poland; Chicago & Florida), delivering multiple project releases and customer commitments. Built the Chicago apps (Android/iOS/Windows) team ground up to deliver the mobile apps for unified communications.
- Transformed the team to operate with start-up mentality by applying agile methodologies with customer focus & simplicity to meet aggressive customer contract commitments.
- Increased velocity & efficiency with CI/CD and devops mindset accountability. Iterative development across solution level with leverage of SAFe agile resulted in product maturation in smaller chunks and delivering quality product.
- R&D budget planning, management and building global teams to achieve the goals.
- Drove a collaborative environment across global teams and worked closely with product management, UX design & multiple product teams for successful delivery of solutions (backend and customer facing apps).

Vinu Ramasamy Page 2

Motorola Inc., **Products and Common Platform**, Schaumburg, IL **Engineering Manager**, **Senior Manager**

2010 - 2014

Led the device management business strategy and product development across all MSI devices portfolio.

Strategic Innovation & Product Roadmap

- Led, implemented and deployed software licensing strategy for subscribers and applications. Enabled additional software revenue opportunities for feature up-sell.
- Initiated, and created radio management application solution for public safety and commercial verticals, enabling additional revenue and hosted service opportunities for subscribers. ~\$5M+ revenue in the first full year; continuing to generate revenue

Operational Efficiency & Product Development

- Improved efficiency and productivity of the customer programming software team freed up ~100 resources globally and self-funded the development of common platform for radio management application.
- Drove the culture change across global teams (~200 engineers spread across China, Schaumburg & Florida) to operate as ONE team and built a high performing team, delivering several successful (positive customer feedback) releases across multiple verticals and product portfolio.
- Established common internal end-to-end ALM process leveraging Microsoft TFS suite with deployment of Agile principles. The product was built leveraging MVC and SOA based architecture, primarily C# language and SQL Server database.

Motorola, Inc., Professional and Commercial Sector, Schaumburg, IL **Architect, Team Lead, Section Manager**

2003 - 2009

- Led and built global team (~50 engineers across Schaumburg, China & Penang) and successfully delivered applications for MOTOTRBO subscribers and low tier base station products for configuration and management based on SOA architecture.
- Led the first generation of client / server based battery fleet management application for public safety.
- Collaborated with local regional business teams to work with the customers, gather requirements and help deploy software.
- Create a reusable PC application platform, demonstrating productivity increase and lower engineering cost.

ADDITIONAL RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Motorola Inc., Commercial Sector, Schaumburg, IL **Software Engineer, Senior Software Engineer, Architect**

Kottmann Inc., Scott Airforce Base, IL Team Lead / Senior Software Developer

EDUCATION

Master of Science (MS), Computing and Information Systems, Southern Illinois University, Edwardsville, IL **Bachelor of Engineering (BE)**, Electrical and Electronics Engineering, University of Madras, India

AWARDS AND RECOGNITION

Motorola Solutions Leadership Award (2014) Motorola Solutions Next-Generation Leaders Program (2012-2014) Motorola Solutions - rated as a top performer year over year

COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

Inspiration Corporation, Chicago, IL **Board Member**

Inspiration Corporation provides people who are affected by homelessness and poverty with employment, housing and supportive services. Non-profit organization - www.inspirationcorp.org.